Okay, today's דף daf is ק"ג, kuf gimmel, 103 מנחות. Menachot. We
pick up at the top of ק"ג עמוד א', kuf gimmel amud
aleph, about six lines from the top, at the משנה. mishnah. And
let's take a look. We're dealing with people that take certain vows
and then they don't exactly match those vows relating to מנחות, menachot,
and what are the consequences? So, here's what our משנה mishnah says:
האומר הרי עלי מנחה מן השעורים יביא מן החיטים.
Ha'omer harei alai mincha
min hase'orim yavi min hachittim. So, somebody takes a vow. Before, it
was somebody took a vow מרחשת marcheshet and brought מחבת; machavat; it
didn't match. Here, it's somebody who's taking a vow which the vow
itself—not what the person did, the vow itself—doesn't match what is required.
So, if somebody says, 'I obligate myself with a מנחה mincha of
barley,' there is no free-will מנחה mincha of barley. It's a מנחת
חוטא minchat choteh or a מנחה mincha by a סוטה sotah that's
barley. So, instead, you have to bring a מנחה. mincha. We sort
of ignore the שעורים se'orim part and you bring a standard מנחה
mincha out of wheat.
קמח יביא סולת. Kemach yavi solet. Somebody takes a vow that, 'I'm
going to bring a מנחה mincha out of bran.' You can't bring
it out of bran; you bring it out of fine flour. בלא
שמן ובלא לבונה יביא שמן ולבונה. Belo shemen uvelo levonah yavi shemen
ulevonah. 'I'm going to—I obligate myself to take a מנחה mincha without
oil and frankincense.' Obviously, that's not possible.
You bring with the oil and the frankincense.
חצי עישרון יביא עישרון שלם. Chatzi issaron yavi issaron shalem. If you
say, 'I'm obligating myself in a half of an עישרון,' issaron, you
can only bring a מנחה mincha in full units of עשרונות, issronot,
so you have to bring a full עישרון. issaron. Now, the question
with all of this is why? Why don't we just say you
took a vow and the vow was like meaningless? So, that's the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask that question. Why are we willing
to obligate you in a מנחה mincha and ignore the other part?
Why don't we just say the package that you obligated yourself for
is meaningless and the vow isn't binding? So, that's essentially
עישרון ומחצה יביא שניים—excuse issaron umemtza yavi shenayim me, the last case.
If he says, 'I'm going to bring an עישרון issaron and a
half,' in that case, you bring two. That's particularly the most interesting,
I would say, because until this point you could say: ignore the
part of the vow that's not relevant, the
addition—out of barley, out of bran—just cut those words off, and you
basically said you wanted to bring a מנחה. mincha. But here, how
do we get from an עישרון issaron and a half to round
up to two עשרונות? issronot? All right, so we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara.
רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon poter. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts,
and it seems to be going on all of them. שלא התנדב
כדרך המתנדבים. Shelo hitnadev kederech hamitnadbim. You did not take a vow
like normal people take a vow. Meaning, what you obligated yourself for
is not a possible מנחה. mincha. We look at the entire word
you said and they don't work as a package, so we throw
the whole thing out. Even an עישרון issaron and a half doesn't
work because it has to be out of full units of עשרונות.
issronot. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So, the
גמרא Gemara asks the obvious question: אמאי? Amai? Why is he have
to bring anything in this משנה? mishnah? נדר ופתחו עמו. Neder upitcho
imo. It's the vow with the opening there. Meaning, the fact that
you said something—you look at רש"י, Rashi, three lines down, נדר ופתחו
עמו: neder upitcho imo: אם הנדר אמר פתח, im haneder amar petach,
with his נדר neder he's saying like an opening to get out
of it,
שמתחרט בו, shemit charet bo, that that makes it sound like he's
showing that he clearly has remorse, he wants to reverse his decision.
דכיון דאמר מן השעורים אמינא דאין בדעתו להביא כלום דאדם יודע שאין
מנחה מן השעורים. Dekivan de'amar min hase'orim amina de'ein beda'ato lehavi klum
de'adam yode'a she'ein mincha min hase'orim. That now, now we see that
you're saying that barley—clearly you didn't really mean to do anything because
you know there isn't a מנחה mincha of barley—so we read your
words when you say 'barley' as an attempt to retract. Okay, now
that's interesting because that gets to the question of are you able
to retract? And that's what this very, very long תוספות Tosafot is
that starts on the עמוד ב'. amud bet. You know, maybe the
reason here that you're bound is maybe
you did intend to retract, but maybe retraction doesn't work. Okay, but
anyway, but that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Since clearly you're
retracting, we should throw it out. You know, another way of understanding
it is not that you're retracting, the simple sense: you obligated yourself
in something meaningless, and there's no such נדר—there's neder no such מנחה
mincha with שעורים, se'orim, and therefore you didn't obligate yourself in anything.
Either way, the question is: why is this binding? So, let's see
what the גמרא Gemara answers. אמר חזקיה הא מני בית שמאי היא
דאמרי תפוס לשון ראשון.
Amar Chizkiyah ha mani
Beit Shammai hi de'amri tafos lashon rishon.
This is חזקיה; Chizkiyah; this is בית שמאי Beit Shammai that says
that you basically seize the first part of what the person said.
He said, 'הרי עלי מנחה,' Harei alai mincha, you obligated yourself for
a מנחה. mincha. The rest of it doesn't work together, so we
ignore the rest of it. The, the first part, as soon as
it comes out of your mouth, is—binds you. And anything you said
afterwards doesn't redefine it, isn't a retraction; you're already seized by the
first words that you said. Where do you see this about בית
שמאי? Beit Shammai? דתנן, Detnan, taught in the משנה mishnah in נזיר:
Nazir: הריני נזיר מן הגרוגרות ומן הדבילה. Hareini nazir min hagerogerot umin
hadeveilah.
Somebody says, 'I'm going to be a נזיר nazir from like, you
know, not eating like pressed figs or pressed dates' or whatever. So,
obviously there's no such נזירות neziroot of that. There's a נזירות neziroot
to not, you know, have grapes or wine. So, similar type of
an idea: you try to reconstruct what the נזירות neziroot is. in
a way that is not the category the תורה Torah recognizes. So
what's the הלכה? halacha? בית שמאי אומרים נזיר, Beit Shammai omerim nazir,
you're a נזיר. nazir. How could that be? Because we ignore the
part of your statement that isn't relevant and we just focused on
the first words. That's תפוס לשון ראשון. tfos lashon rishon. ובית הלל
אומרים אינו נזיר, U'Beit Hillel omerim eino nazir, and בית הלל Beit
Hillel says he's not a נזיר. nazir. So that basically has the
whole סתם משנה stam mishnah בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, which is interesting
that a סתם משנה stam mishnah would be בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
and the only one to argue on it would be רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Okay, that's חזקיה's Chizkiya take. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא
בית הלל. Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu teima Beit Hillel. No, our משנה
mishnah could go like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, that usually is words
it looks at like the whole statement. But here's the case. באומר:
B'omer: אילו הייתי יודע שאין נודרים כך לא הייתי נודר כך אלא
כך. ilu hayiti yodea she'ein nodrin kach, lo hayiti noder kach ela
kach. Had I realized, I had genuinely thought that you could make
a מנחה mincha out of barley. I genuinely thought there would be
an option to make a מנחה mincha without, you know, oil or
frankincense. All right? And had I realized that that was not a
possibility, of course I would have just obligated myself in a simple
מנחה. mincha. So what does that mean? We do look at the
whole statement. We do understand that what you said was something that
isn't binding. But we now here's the question. When he says באומר,
b'omer, do we specifically go ahead and ask him? You know, if
so, you would imagine that the משנה mishnah would have said, 'If
he says that this is what he meant.' So the sense one
gets here is not so much that you ask him, but that
we we like assume, right? And it makes a lot more sense.
Somebody who says 'I'm not going to eat figs and dates and
I'm a נזיר', nazir it's like, really? How okay, like can we
assume that had you known that a נזיר nazir was from wine
and also from hair and also from dead bodies, etc., can we
assume that that's what you would have wanted? Not so clear. But
if somebody says 'I want to bring a מנחה mincha from barley,
from bran', you know, those are like a little less I mean,
obviously it's a little cheaper, but they're a little less central. And
saying, 'No, you still have to bring a מנחה mincha from flour
and fine flour, etc.' is not a like major change in what
the person was saying. So it seems a way to understand what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying is not that person explicitly said
it, but in these cases we can assume that that is what
he would have wanted. Had he realized it wouldn't have been binding,
he would have accepted upon himself a straight מנחה. mincha. Now, even
if that's the case and we can assume that, there's still a
problem that he didn't say it, right? So you have to say
a נדר neder for it to be binding. But that can work
because he did say הרי עלי מנחה. harei alai mincha. So, you
know, so actually the way to understand רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
not like we just objectively cut off everything afterwards that didn't work,
but which is like the בית שמאי Beit Shammai part, but in
a case where we can assume that you would not have added
that end part had you known it wouldn't have worked, then we
can say we'll focus on the first part הרי עלי מנחה harei
alai mincha and say that's that's what you really meant. Okay? So
it has the same result as בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but it
only works in a case where it's reasonable to assume that that's
what you really would have wanted was just the מנחה mincha if
the other part would not have worked. So the debate by נזיר
nazir still works because there we can't assume you would have wanted
to be a straight נזיר. nazir. Okay, so that really works well.
The part that it doesn't work so well with, we must admit,
is the last case about an עשרון isaron and a half that
you bring two עשרונות. isronot. Because there, even if you could say,
'Well, what it means according to, you know, you know, according to
בית הלל Beit Hillel is since the person wanted to bring more
than one עשרון, isaron, had he realized that you could only bring
in whole units, he would have bought wanted to say two עשרונות.'
isronot.
Even if we can totally assume that's true, he didn't say two
עשרונות. isronot. So it's very nice what he would have wanted to
say, but where's the actual נדר neder that he took that obligates
him in two עשרונות? isronot? So let's hold that as a question.
Okay, but right now we'll get back to that. But right now
we
have this debate, two ways of reading the משנה mishnah of why
you're still bound. Either by בית שמאי Beit Shammai we just look
at the first half that works and we ignore the second half,
or
בית הלל Beit Hillel that when the second half doesn't work, if
we can assume you would have just wanted the first half, then
that's what will be binding. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר חזקיה: לא שנו אלא דאמר מנחה מן השעורים.
Amar Chizkiya: lo shanu ela d'amar
mincha min hase'orim.
The case of our משנה mishnah where you're bound by it is
if you say a מנחה mincha from barley. אבל אמר מנחה מן
העדשים, Aval amar mincha min ha'adashim, if you say מנחה mincha out
of lentils, לא, lo, then that doesn't bind you. Why? Because presumably
everybody knows you can't bring a מנחה mincha out of lentils. But
the גמרא's Gemara going to so obviously you didn't mean it. But
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, 'But wait a minute. חזקיה Chizkiya
goes like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't care
whether you meant it or not. He just focuses on the words.'
מכדי, Michdi, says the גמרא, Gemara, let's take a look. חזקיה כמאן
אמר לשמעתיה? Chizkiya k'man amar l'shmeiteih?
Who did חזקיה Chizkiya say, you know, what was according to whom
did חזקיה Chizkiya explain the משנה? mishnah? כבית שמאי, k'Beit Shammai, like
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. ובית שמאי משום תפוס לשון ראשון הוא. U'Beit
Shammai mishum tfos lashon rishon hu. But בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, it's
because just we just grab your first words. We don't care what
you were thinking, what you might have intended. It's just you said
מנחה, mincha, that binds you. Okay? מה לי מן השעורים מה לי
מן העדשים? mah li min hase'orim mah li min ha'adashim? Why should
it matter what you said afterwards? Barley, lentils? Lentils out of elephants,
who cares what you would have said? You said the word מנחה,
mincha, הריני, ha-reni, you know, you're obligating yourself מנחה, mincha, period, that
bound you. So the גמרא Gemara says הדר ביה, hadar beh, you
know what? You're right. It doesn't work according to בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, that distinction of barley versus lentils. חזקיה Chizkiyahu reversed himself, he
decided רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was right, it really is going according
to בית הלל Beit Hillel about what you would have wanted had
you had had known. Okay? ומאי טעמא הדר ביה, u'mai ta'ama hadar
beh, what motivated him to reverse his explanation? אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
מתניתין קשיתיה, matnitin kashyateih,
because the language of the משנה Mishnah sort of pushed in that
direction. That's bothered him. מאי איריא דתני מנחה מן השעורים, mai irya
detani mincha min ha-se'orim,
why did the משנה Mishnah give a case of out of barley,
which it's a type of thing that people could reasonably make a
mistake about? Why didn't it tell you a bigger חידוש, chiddush, that
even if you said a מנחה mincha out of lentils, you still
have to bring a מנחה? mincha? אלא שמע מינה משום דטעי, ela
shema mina mishum detaei, it must mean, since it gave an example
of things that people could reasonably make mistakes about, it must be
that the משנה Mishnah is assuming that the reason you are bound
is because this is a reasonable mistake. Okay, and that works according
to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. You know, you really wanted to bring
a מנחה mincha and you reasonably thought that it could be this
thing, you made a mistake, but ultimately you wanted to bring a
מנחה. mincha. So if it's what you ultimately wanted and there's an
area where we understand it was a bit of a mistake, so
we go by what you ultimately wanted. And that makes sense why
it is out of barley and that that's within that range. But
when you say lentils, clearly that's absurd. You might have said I'm
going to bring a מנחה mincha out of elephants, and therefore clearly
if we're going by what you really meant, you didn't really obligate
yourself in a מנחה. mincha. So if the משנה Mishnah suggests that
only barley you're bound and lentils you're not, that works according to
בית הלל Beit Hillel where we ask the question, what did you
really mean? Okay? אלא שמע מינה משום דטעי, ela shema mina mishum
detaei,
the explanation of the משנה Mishnah is because you made a mistake.
Oh, I didn't realize, had I realized, and therefore the focus is
on what do we think you really meant. בסעורים טעי, bi-se'orim taei,
and you could have made that a mistake by barley. דעדשים לא
טעי, di-adashim lo taei, but not by lentils. So since lentils was
just absurd and not a mistake, clearly you're not binding yourself. Okay,
so because, so in the end חזקיה Chizkiyahu came around to רבי
יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position. Since the משנה Mishnah suggests that you're only
bound in a case of barley and not in a case of
lentils, since by בית שמאי Beit Shammai it doesn't matter what you
were thinking, you just go by the words, that distinction wouldn't make
sense. It only works according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. רבי יוחנן
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, אפילו מן
העדשים. afillu min ha-adashim.
No, according to, in the משנה, Mishnah, even if you said I'm
going to bring a מנחה mincha out of lentils, you're still bound
to bring a מנחה. mincha. Like everybody is saying the opposite of
what you would expect from their position. So the גמרא Gemara says
מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. רבי יוחנן כמאן אמרה לשמעתיה, Rabbi
Yochanan k'man amrah l'shmateih, according to whom did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
give his explanation? How did he explain the משנה? Mishnah? כבית הלל,
k'Beit Hillel, like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, that it's because we look
at what deep down you really meant. ובית הלל משום דטעי, u'Beit
Hillel mishum detaei, and בית הלל's Beit Hillel because, whoops, I made
a mistake, but I really wanted to bring a מנחה. mincha. Okay,
so if that's true, how do you say that by the case
of lentils? בסעורים טעי בעדשים לא טעי, bi-se'orim taei bi-adashim lo taei,
by barley people make a mistake, that works, but by lentils people
don't make a mistake. So if we're going like בית הלל, Beit
Hillel, when you said lentils you were saying something absurd, clearly it
wasn't a mistake, so clearly you never really meant to obligate yourself
in anything. So why is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying that lentils
would bind you? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. לדבריו דחזקיה
קאמר ליה, li-devarav de-Chizkiyahu ka-amar leh,
he's saying to חזקיה Chizkiyahu according to your thinking. So according to
you חזקיה, Chizkiyahu, that we're assuming the משנה Mishnah was בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, you know, so I'm going to tell you that it's
אפילו מן העדשים. afillu min ha-adashim. You can read the משנה Mishnah
like you wanted, you can read the משנה Mishnah like בית שמאי
Beit Shammai and you can say that yes, according to בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, you'll even be bound by עדשים adashim because you just
focus on the first language. But why did you retract yourself? Because
the משנה Mishnah suggests just barley, not lentils. I'm going to tell
you, you can stick with your position, it is בית שמאי Beit
Shammai and lentils also you would be bound, and it works with
the משנה. Mishnah. How is
that? דילמא לא מיבעיא קאמר, dilma lo mibaya ka-amar, maybe the
משנה's Mishnah saying
it goes without saying, again working with בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. לא מיבעיא מן העדשים דאיכא למימר הדר הוא דהדר
ביה ותפס לשון ראשון. lo mibaya min ha-adashim de-ika lemeimar hadar hu
de-hadar beh ve-tafas lashon rishon.
If you're בית שמאי Beit Shammai you could say look if the
guy says lentils... So heck, what do I care what he says
afterwards? You said מנחה, Minchah, you're bound by it. Lentils, of course,
is totally absurd. So of course, I'm going to ignore that. That's
like a complete retraction and that gets ignored and you said מנחה
Minchah and you're bound by it. So it was obvious according to
בית שמאי Beis Shammai that lentils you would be bound, because it's
obviously like a retraction or new statement and it obviously gets ignored.
תפס לשון ראשון. Tfos lashon rishon. So the משנה Mishnah didn't say
lentils according to, and it could be like בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
It just doesn't say lentils because it's obvious. Why is barley less
obvious? אלא אפילו מן השעורים נמי, Ela afilu min hasiorim nami, even
when you say barley, we ignore it according to בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. Why is that a little less obvious? דילמא למימר מיהו דקטעי,
Dilma lemeimar mi'hu d'katai, because maybe you could say in that case,
it's clear he really was making a mistake. Meaning, maybe בית שמאי'ס
Beis Shammai's idea of תפס לשון ראשון Tfos lashon rishon is when
the second thing is clearly some type of a second statement and
a retraction, and then we ignore it. But when the second thing
clearly shows a type what the person's mistake and intent was from
the beginning, maybe we would look at the entire statement as one.
Okay, which makes sense. If somebody's trying to take it back, retract,
sorry, no backsies. Okay, תפס לשון ראשון. Tfos lashon rishon. But if
clearly somebody meant something else and had something else in mind, maybe
we really would give it weight. אפילו הכי, Afilu hachi, תפס לשון
ראשון. Tfos lashon rishon. Nevertheless, we would still ignore we still ignore
it. בית שמאי'ס Beis Shammai's תפס לשון ראשון Tfos lashon rishon is
absolute. Whether the second half of your statement is a clear retraction,
like lentils, or whether it shows what you always had in mind,
like barley, it doesn't matter. We ignore the second half. If the
second half doesn't work, we just focus on the first half. Okay,
so to review. The משנה Mishnah could be read either בית שמאי
Beis Shammai or בית הלל. Beis Hillel. According to בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, it doesn't matter what you're thinking, you just go by the
first half. And therefore, whether you say barley or lentils, you would
be bound. Okay, maybe the משנה Mishnah said barley, but it's because
maybe lentils was even more obvious because that was a retraction. But
either way you would be bound. And according to בית הלל, Beis
Hillel,
we
could read it to say that the reason you go by the
first part is because we understand that deep down that's really what
you intended, had you understood the הלכה. Halacha. That in a case
of barley, but in a case where we can understand that you
were making a mistake. But in a case of lentils, genuinely according
to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, we genuinely would reject the whole statement,
you weren't making a mistake, so the whole thing gets rejected. Okay,
very good. So let's see now what the גמרא Gemara says.
Top
of קג עמוד ב. Kuf gimmel amud beis. אמר זעירי, Amar Zeiri,
said זעירי. Zeiri. לא שנו, Lo shanu,
the
fact that in the משנה Mishnah you get bound by the first
half of your statement,
whether
according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai or בית הלל. Beis Hillel. לא
שנו אלא דאמר מנחה, Lo shanu ela d'amar Minchah, you said מנחה
מן השעורים. Minchah min hasiorim. מנחה, Minchah, you like, you know, you
know, mean what was the other example? א מנחה מן השעורים, A
Minchah min hasiorim, מנחה מן הקמח. Minchah min hakamach. You said the
word מנחה. Minchah. אבל לא אמר מנחה, Aval lo amar Minchah, if
you didn't say מנחה, Minchah, לא, Lo, you would not be bound.
Now what's the scenario you didn't say מנחה? Minchah? You either said
הרי עלי מן השעורים, Harei alai min hasiorim, הרי עלי מן הקמח,
Harei alai min hakamach, you know, and the word מנחה Minchah was
somehow implied. What type of vow are you taking when you say
מן השעורים min hasiorim or מן הקמח? min hakamach? Clearly you mean
a מנחה. Minchah. That's one possibility. Or רש"י Rashi said another possibility
is it's a question of סמיכות Smichut or not סמיכות. Smichut. מנחה
מן השעורים Minchah min hasiorim is one thing, מנחת שעורים Minchat siorim
is another thing. So working within the בית שמאי Beis Shammai explanation,
let's focus on that. Okay? That we're just going to cut off
and focus on your first word. Well, that works if you say
מנחה מן השעורים. Minchah min hasiorim. So we throw out the מן
השעורים, min hasiorim, we grab the word מנחה. Minchah. That works. But
if you just said מן השעורים, min hasiorim, there's nothing to grab
you by, there's no way to obligate you. And even if you
said מנחת שעורים, Minchat siorim, there's nothing to grab you by because
מנחת Minchat is not a full word, it's מנחה Minchah of. So
clearly it drags the word שעורים siorim with it. So this only
works if you say מנחה Minchah as a single word and then
מן השעורים. min hasiorim. Okay, then that certainly works according to בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, right? According to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, you could
say who cares? Even if you said מנחת שעורים, Minchat siorim, deep
down, you know, we say you really meant a מנחה סתם. Minchah
stam. Alright, so let's focus now, you know, it could still work
with בית הלל Beis Hillel if בית הלל Beis Hillel at the
end of the day you have to still find which language he
said that is binding him, so maybe even according to בית הלל
Beis Hillel you need a word מנחה Minchah that can bind him.
But we're just going to explain this according to בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. So to say תפס לשון ראשון, Tfos lashon rishon, you need
the word מנחה Minchah by itself so that you can focus in
on it. אבל לא אמר מנחה לא. Aval lo amar Minchah lo.
יתיב רב נחמן וקאמר לה להא שמעתא. Yasiv Rav Nachman vekamar la
l'ha shmaita. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman was sitting and saying over
this explanation, you know, זעירי Zeiri says it's only if you say
the word מנחה, Minchah, then we can, you know, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai can grab you by that word מנחה. Minchah. איתיביה רבא לרב
נחמן, Esiv Rava l'Rav Nachman, so רבא Rava challenged him, can you-
Can you really read the משנה mishna that way? Let's go through
the cases in the משנה. mishna. קמח יביא סולת. Kemach yavi soles.
If the guy said קמח, kemach, notice the משנה mishna doesn't say
מנחה מן הקמח, mincha min hakemach, just says קמח, kemach, okay, bran,
bring fine flour. לאו דלא אמר מנחה? lav delo amar mincha? You
know, the משנה mishna just said if he said קמח, kemach, it
sounds like he just said הרי עלי קמח. harei alai kemach. He
didn't say the word מנחה. mincha. And it still says that we
have it mean that you're obligated in a normal מנחה. mincha. So
the גמרא gemara says לא דאמר מנחה. lo de'amar mincha. No, it
means he said מנחה מן הקמח. mincha min hakemach. Okay, let's look
at the next phrase of the משנה. mishna. בלא שמן ובלא לבונה.
belo shemen u'velo levona. If somebody
without oil and frankincense, יביא שמן ולבונה, yavi shemen u'levona, you have
to bring it with oil and frankincense. מאי לאו דלא אמר מנחה?
mai lav delo amar mincha? Are we talking about that he didn't
say the word מנחה? mincha? That's not in the משנה. mishna. It's
going to be the same question over and over. You're insisting that
he said the word מנחה. mincha. That doesn't appear in the משנה.
mishna. It sounds like the guy just said הרי עלי בלא שמן
ובלא לבונה. harei alai belo shemen u'velo levona. And the idea of
מנחה mincha was implied. So the גמרא gemara says לא דאמר מנחה.
lo de'amar mincha. No, he said the word. Okay, let's keep on
going. חצי עשרון יביא עשרון שלם. chatzi isaron yavi isaron shalem. If
you said half an עשרון, isaron, you bring a full עשרון. isaron.
מאי לאו דלא אמר מנחה? mai lav delo amar mincha? Again, isn't
it just he said הרי עלי חצי עשרון harei alai chatzi isaron
without saying the word מנחה? mincha? לא דאמר מנחה. lo de'amar mincha.
No, he said the word. אי הכי אימא סיפא. ei hachi eima
seifa. Fine, all of that even though it's not in the language
of the text, I can let you get away with. But let's
now look at the last case, okay. עשרון ומחצה יביא שניים. isaron
u'mechetza yavi shnayim. If the guy says I'm obligating myself with an
עשרון isaron and a half, bring, he has to bring
שניים. shnayim. So okay, יביא שניים. yavi shnayim. So כיון דאמר מנחה,
keivan de'amar mincha, if he said מנחה, עשרון ומחצה. mincha isaron u'mechetza,
Now you're saying he said the word מנחה. mincha, So and this
is according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. So he says the word
מנחה, mincha. איחייב ליה בעשרון. ichayev lei be'isaron. That word מנחה mincha,
by itself obligates him in a minimum מנחה, mincha one עשרון. isaron.
כי אמר חצי עשרון לא כלום קאמר.
ki amar chatzi isaron lo
klum ka'amar.
So he said הרי עלי מנחה עשרון וחצי. harei alai mincha isaron
va'chetzi. So the word מנחה mincha, obligated him in an עשרון. isaron.
The word עשרון isaron that he says afterwards is consistent with the
word מנחה. mincha So he's still obligated in one עשרון. isaron. Then
he says the word חצי. chetzi. חצי chetzi doesn't obligate
him, okay. So how is that going to lead to two עשרונות?
isronos? That's the question.
Now
תוספות Tosafot explains how else I would have explained this משנה. mishna.
Because as I've been saying, this is all according to בית שמאי.
Beis Shammai. According to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, you need that word
מנחה mincha. to grab him by it. But according to בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, the key is what was he thinking? And I've been
trying to suggest according to בית הלל Beis Hillel you also needed
a word to hang on, but it doesn't seem like the גמרא
gemara is really fully committed to that. Which is a funny idea.
נדר neder normally depends on the words you say. But it seems
like we can just freely reinterpret it based on what we think
you were saying and what you meant. So according to בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, you don't need the word מנחה. mincha If he would
have said הרי עלי מן השעורים, harei alai min ha'se'orim, we know
what you mean is a מנחה mincha. from חטים. chittim. הרי עלי
מן הקמח, harei alai min hakemach, we know you mean מנחה mincha
from קמח, kemach, even though you didn't say the word מנחה. mincha
So in that case, if you said הרי עלי עשרון harei alai
isaron ומחצה,
we would have said you mean a מנחה mincha. of an עשרון
isaron and a half, but you can't bring an עשרון isaron and
a half. You obviously meant more than one עשרון, isaron, so you
mean two עשרונות. isronos. That would have worked. So if you had
read the משנה mishna בית הלל Beis Hillel and we want to
know what you were thinking, it could have worked. But according to
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, you're saying you need the word to grab
him on, okay, and just the word קמח kemach or שעורים se'orim
is not enough. You need the word מנחה. mincha Okay. Then if
he said מנחה עשרון ומחצה, minchah issaron u'mechtzah, מנחה עשרון mincha isaron
is one מנחה, mincha. and מחצה mechetza is just the word מחצה.
mechetza. מחצה mechetza is not enough to grab him on. So according
to בית שמאי Beis Shammai that you need the word, you can't
go by what he is thinking. How do you get from עשרון
ומחצה isaron u'mechetza. to be two עשרונות? isronos? Very good question. So
let's see what the גמרא gemara says. לא כלום קאמר הוא. lo
klum ka'amar hu. So the גמרא gemara says לא צריכא דאמר הרי
עלי מנחה חצי עשרון ועשרון. lo tzericha de'amar harei alai mincha chatzi
isaron ve'isaron.
You say it in the reverse order. You don't say עשרון ומחצה,
isaron u'mechetza, you say a half of an עשרון isaron and an
עשרון. isaron. So what's that going to get? דכיון דאמר מנחה, de'keivan
de'amar mincha, as soon as again remember it's בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
we're focusing on the words themselves objectively binding you. So when you
say the word מנחה, mincha, איחייב ליה בעשרון, ichayev lei be'isaron, that
obligates you in a minimum מנחה mincha, of one עשרון. isaron. כי
אמר חצי עשרון, ki amar chatzi isaron, then the next word you
say is half of an עשרון, isaron, לא כלום קאמר. lo klum
ka'amar. That word doesn't bind you at all. It's a meaningless word,
okay, in this context. כי הדר אמר עשרון, ki hadar amar isaron,
and then you say the final עשרון, isaron, מייתי עשרון אחרינא. meisi
isaron achrina. So that saying הרי עלי עשרון harei alai issaron obligates
you. הרי עלי שעורים harei alai se'orim doesn't obligate you because there's
no מנחה mincha of שעורים. se'orim. הרי עלי קמח harei alai kemach
doesn't obligate you. הרי עלי harei alai עשרון issaron does obligate you.
So if you said מנחה mincha עשרון ומחצה, isaron u'mechetza מנחת עשרון
minchat issaron is one package, one עשרון issaron and then you should
never get up to two. But if you say מנחה חצי ועשרון,
minchah chatzi v'issaron, you know, מחצה, mechtzah, you know, חצי עשרון ועשרון,
chatzi issaron v'issaron, מנחה minchah obligates you, חצי עשרון chatzi issaron is
meaningless, and עשרון issaron obligates you again. Okay. חצי ועשרון לא כלום
קאמר כי הדר אמר עשרון מאי עשרון אחרינא.
chatzi v'issaron lo klum ka'amar
ki hadar amar issaron mai issaron achrina. אי הכי, i hachi, says
the Gemara, if
that's true, רבי שמעון פוטר שלא התנדב כדרך המתנדבים, Rabbi Shimon poter
she'lo hitnadev k'derech ha'mitnadvim, Rabbi
Shimon totally exempts you from all these cases because it's not a,
he looks at the whole statement and it's not a meaningful obligation.
Okay, but the Gemara says אמאי, amai, why? So what's the question?
The question is if you would have said, you know, עשרון ומחצה,
isaron u'mechetza, so fine, we get the idea that that's like one
unit and עשרון issaron and a half and there's no such thing,
and Rabbi Shimon says I look at the whole statement and I
throw it out. But now that you are suggesting that what he
says is, you know, מנחה חצי ועשרון ועשרון, minchah chatzi v'issaron v'issaron,
so then says תוספות Tosafot that's not one statement that you look,
this is how תוספות Tosafot explain, it's not one statement that you
look at the totality of it. That's clearly two statements. מנחה חצי
עשרון ועשרון
minchah chatzi
issaron v'issaron clearly sounds like if you said הרי עלי מנחת עשרון
ומחצה harei alai minchat issaron u'mechtzah that's one statement, an עשרון issaron,
and a half, and he says I'm going to look at the
whole statement, that's meaningless, don't do anything. But if it's הרי עלי
מנחה חצי עשרון ועשרון, harei alai minchah chatzi issaron v'issaron, it sounds
like you're talking about two things. One מנחה minchah of חצי עשרון,
chatzi issaron, okay, that's nothing, and an עשרון, issaron well, the last
עשרון issaron, should at least obligate you. That's a separate statement. That's
not part of the whole statement. So why does Rabbi Shimon say
that you get totally off? So the Gemara says אמר רבא רבי
שמעון בשיטת רבי יוסי אמרה דאמר אף בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס. Amar
Rava Rabbi Shimon b'shitat Rabbi Yosi amrah d'amar af b'gmar devarav adam
nitpas. Rabbi Shimon goes like Rabbi Yosi who says you even go
by the end of your statement. And again, the way תוספות Tosafot
explains this is we always understood
that
Rabbi Shimon was looking at the whole statement and he said if
the statement as a whole doesn't make sense, you throw it out.
מנחת שעורים, minchat se'orim, sorry,
throw out. מנחת חצי עשרון, minchat chatzi issaron, throw out. You know,
מנחת קמח, minchat kemach, throw out.
But
if you make two statements, then we might say, well, okay, the
first one throw out, go by the second one. And that's and
when you say מנחה חצי עשרון ועשרון, minchah chatzi issaron v'issaron, at
least the second statement עשרון, issaron that you should go by. And
here he says no, he follows Rabbi Yosi who says even when
you make two statements, like they're in the same sentence but they're
two statements, we take the whole package and treat it as one.
And since we take the whole package and treat it as one,
then even in that case, you know, there is the you look
at everything as one unit and there's no מנחה minchah of an
עשרון isaron. and a half and you throw it out. Okay. So
in the end, we basically have according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
you're grabbing on the words, you don't care what he thinks, you
don't care is it a reasonable mistake, not a reasonable mistake, did
he say barley, did he say lentils, doesn't matter, you just grab
the word, but you need the word, you need him to say
מנחה. minchah. Without the word, you can't obligate him. According to בית
הלל, Beis Hillel, you go by what did you really mean, what
would you really have meant had you understood. So A, it's limited
to cases where you would have made a reasonable mistake like barley,
not by lentils. But then B, on the other hand, he's willing
to obligate you even without the magic word. Even if you didn't
say מנחה, minchah, even if you just said שעורים, se'orim, we understand
that's what you what you really meant was a מנחה minchah and
we would obligate you by that. Okay. And Rabbi Shimon says you
look at the whole statement and if the whole statement doesn't work,
you throw it out. And according to the end of the Gemara,
even if there are really two statements side by side, you look
at them together and if they don't work, you throw them out.
All right. Let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishnah.
מתנדב אדם מנחה של ששים עשרון ומביא
בכלי אחד. mitnadev adam minchah shel shishim issaron u'meivi bichli echad. A
person can take a מנחה minchah up to sixty עשרונות issronot and
bring them all in one vessel. Okay. אם אמר, im amar, and
we'll read the parentheses, הרי עלי ששים עשרון מביא בכלי אחד. harei
alai shishim issaron meivi bichli echad. If he said it, you bring
them all in one vessel. But אם אמר הרי עלי ששים ואחד,
im amar harei alai shishim v'echad, if he said I am obligating
myself in a מנחה minchah of sixty-one, okay, and you might think
since he just said a מנחה minchah of sixty-one, he's obligated to
bring it all in a single vessel, no. Sixty is the limit.
מביא ששים בכלי אחד ואחד בכלי אחר. meivi shishim bichli echad v'echad
bichli acher. You bring sixty in one vessel and one in the
other. Not clear if this is related to the previous issue of
the משנה, mishnah, בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, how
much are we reinterpreting the נדר? neder? You didn't say explicitly כלי
אחד, kli echad, you just said ששים ואחד. shishim v'echad. Anyway, but
we are going to interpret it in a way that makes sense,
which is A מנחה mincha of sixty and a מנחה mincha of
one, because a מנחה mincha of sixty-one is not possible. Now, why
is a מנחה mincha of sixty-one not possible? So let's take a
look. שכן הציבור מביא ביום טוב הראשון של חג שחל להיות בשבת
ששים ואחד,
sheken hatzibur meivi beyom tov harishon
shel chag shechal lihyos beshabbos shishim ve'echad, because there is a one
case in which a communal sacrifice can have of the מנחת נסכים,
minchas nesachim, you know, the flour and oil that came with the
sacrifices, that it can have up to sixty-one עשרונות. esronos. What is
the case? The first day of סוכות Sukkos on שבת. Shabbos. How
does it work? So take a look at רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
spells it out. First רש"י Rashi on the משנה. mishna. So you
know, the first day of סוכות, Sukkos, you have that big sacrifice.
It has thirteen cows, fourteen sheep, etc. So thirteen cows is ל"ט
עשרונים. lamed tes esronim. So for every cow the מנחת נסכים minchas
nesachim is שלשה עשרונים לפר. shlosha esronim lapar. So three times thirteen
is
thirty-nine. שלשה עשרונים לפר. shlosha esronim lapar. ולי"ד כבשים, ule'yud daled kvasim,
the fourteen sheep, so י"ד עשרונים. yud daled esronim. Each sheep is
one עשרון. isaron So thirty-nine and fourteen is fifty-three. הרי נ"ג. harei
nun gimmel. Then you have two rams, שני אילים. shnei eilim. Each
ram gets two
עשרונות. esronos. Okay? ארבע עשרונות. arba esronos. So now we're up to
fifty-seven. הרי נ"ז. harei nun zayin. ולשני תמידים, uleshnei tmiddim, the two
תמידים, tmiddim, each one is a כבש, keves, so that's one more
עשרון isaron per
lamb. שניים. shnayim. So that's two more. ולשני כבשי מוסף uleshnei kivsei
musaf of שבת, Shabbos, but it's שבת, Shabbos, so that's two more
lambs. שניים. shnayim. It's another two. So fifty-seven and two and two,
הרי ששים ואחד, harei shishim ve'echad, sixty-one. So since there could be
a time when the ציבור tzibur brings the קרבנות korbanos of the
day is a total of sixty-one עשרונות, esronos, we don't want a
private person to ever bring a more total than the ציבור tzibur
would bring in one day. So it's like a רבני rabbinic limit.
All right, and presumably based on that we will make that restriction
and even perhaps reinterpret your vow. That's what the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says. שהרי הציבור מביא ביום טוב הראשון של חג שחל להיות
בשבת ששים ואחד, דיו ליחיד שיפחת מן הציבור אחד. sheharei hatzibur meivi
beyom tov harishon shel chag shechal lihyos beshabbos shishim ve'echad, dayo leyachid
sheyipaches min hatzibur echad. You know,
a private person at least one less than the ציבור. tzibur. You
don't need to be as much as the community. אמר רבי שמעון,
amar Rabbi Shimon, said רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, ולא, הרי אלו לפרים
ואלו לכבשים? velo, harei elu laparim ve'elu likvasim? One minute, but the
ציבור tzibur never brings the sixty-one together. Some of it is for
cows and some of it is for sheep, and you can't mix
them together because the cows get more proportional oil per עשרון isaron.
than the sheep does. Okay? The cow gets, you
know,
three עשרונות esronos for the פר par and a half of a
הין hin of oil which is six לוג. log. So it gets
two לוג log per עשרון. isaron The כבש keves gets one עשרון
isaron and a quarter of a הין hin which is three לוג,
log, so it's a three to one. Oh, excuse me, I got
it wrong. The כבש keves has more oil per עשרון isaron than
the cow, okay? So he says, you know, you would never mix
them together because then the proportions would be wrong. You have to
keep them separate. Okay? ולא, הרי אלו לפרים ואלו לכבשים, ואינן נבללים
זה עם זה? velo, harei elu laparim ve'elu likvasim, ve'einan nivlalim zeh
im zeh?
You can't mix them together because they have different consistencies and you
would invalidate them. So you never have a מנחה mincha of a
ציבור tzibur of sixty-one עשרונות. esronos. אלא, ella, here's the real reason.
It's interesting. Everybody agrees that there's a sixty limit. They're trying to
figure out why. So here's what he says. Here's what the real
reason is. אלא עד ששים יכולים להבלל. ella ad shishim yecholim lehibalel.
Until sixty you can mix it well with oil. More than sixty
עשרונות esronos you can't mix well with oil. Now that's a little
strange because isn't the proportion of the עשרון isaron to the oil
constant? So who cares how big it is? So רש"י Rashi says
no, this is going according to the position of רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that says no matter how much flour
you bring you only bring one לוג log of oil. So according
to him once you have sixty-one עשרונות esronos of flour it won't
mix well with just one לוג log of
oil. All right, so that's why it's a limit because you have
to do בלילה, belila, you have to mix the flour with oil
and at that proportion you won't be able to mix
it. אמרו לו, amru lo, so the sages said back to him,
ששים נבללים וששים ואחד אין נבללים? shishim nivlalim veshishim ve'echad ein nivlalim?
What? One different עשרון isaron makes a difference? Sixty can be mixed
with a לוג log of oil but sixty-one can't? Like you know
if you can do sixty you can do sixty-one. So אמר להם,
amar lahem, he said to them, כל מדות חכמים כן. kol middos
chachamim ken. What do you mean? That's always the הלכה. halacha. We
have actual rules and limits. You know, we have a cutoff date.
You have to be born before December 31st. You have to be
this high to get onto the ride you know in the amusement
park. You know, there are rules. You could always say, well, it's
just off by a little bit. And the next person will be
just off a little bit by them. At some point you draw
the line. So he says that's the way, you know, the amounts
by the sages. the Sages work. ארבעים סאה הוא טובל Arba'im se'ah
hu tovel וארבעים סאה חסר קורטוב אינו יכול לטבול בהן. ve'arba'im se'ah
chaser kortov eino yachol litvol bahen.
If you have somebody has 40 סאה se'ah of water, you can
go into the מקווה. mikveh. 40 סאה se'ah minus a thimble, you
can't go to the מקווה. mikveh. So you have to draw limits
and you have to say X works and anything less than X
doesn't. Now there is still a little difference between these because here
we're just we're just describing the physical ability to mix it. You
know, other times when we say a כזית kezayit is Y, because
that's the minimum amount that defines eating, or that's a standard size
that defines what's the standard for X. Okay, but we understand that
it's meant to represent a standard. Here the question is practically can
it mix or not? But even within there, you could say look,
there is going to get a certain point where it can't mix.
Okay? So there is going to be some line, and I'm going
to tell you the line is 60. Is it, you know, and
and yes, and one more thing, it will not reasonably mix. So
that seems like a pretty good argument. I should note that there's
a question. I explained this according to רש"י Rashi that it's going
like רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that says it's
60 עשרונות isronot of flour with one לוג log of oil. But
there's elsewhere רש"י Rashi says we could even be going according to
the one that says it's proportional. You know, one עשרון isaron with
one לוג log of oil and 60 עשרון isaron with 60 לוג
log of oil and 61 עשרון isaron with, you know, 61 לוג
log of oil. And if so, it's always going to be proportional.
So what does that mean you can't mix it? You know, but
even there you could say, look, you did not have industrial-sized mixers.
If you have to mix it with hands, you know, when it's
so so large it could just be that it's too big to
be able to mix it well. Okay, but it does work better
if you say that the לוג log of oil is always fixed.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. שאל זו למעלה מרבי
יהודה בר אלעאי. Sh'al zu lema'la miRabbi Yehuda bar Ilai. The question
was raised in the presence of רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Rabbi Yehuda
bar Ilai, which is standard רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. מנין לאומר הרי
עלי ששים ואחד מביא ששים בכלי אחד ואחד בכלי אחד. Minal le'omer
harei alai shishim ve'echad mevi shishim bikhli echad ve'echad bikhli echad.
If somebody says I'm obligating myself in a מנחה mincha of 61,
how do we know that it means a מנחה mincha of 60
plus a מנחה mincha of one, that we don't just say that
it means a standard, you know, מנחה mincha of of what do
you call it, a standard a full size of
61. פתח רבי יהודה בר אלעאי. Patach Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai. So
רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai,
you know, opened up the discussion. ראש המדברים בכל מקום. Rosh hamedabrim
bechol makom. The person who had the right to speak first under
all in all gatherings. That's a very interesting phrase. Why is it?
Because the גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbat tells the story that when
the sages gathered, you know, רבי יהודה בר אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda bar
Ilai said, you know, how great is this nation, the Romans, and
look at all that they have done for us, and that sort
of gave him the right to, you know, one might probably because
the Romans insisted on it, gave him the right to always be
the first one to open up the discussions.
Anyway, what did he say? ואמר שכן מצינו ציבור מביאים ביום טוב
הראשון של חג שחל להיות בשבת ששים ואחד, Ve'amar sheken matzinu tzibbur
mevi'im beyom tov harishon shel chag shechal lihyot beShabbat shishim ve'echad,
because the community brings its communal sacrifice 61 עשרונות isronot for all
of the sacrifices on סוכות Sukkot that falls on שבת. Shabbat. דיו
ליחיד שיפחות מן הציבור אחד. Dayo leyachid sheyiphos min hatzibbur echad. So
a private individual should at least be a little less than the
ציבור. tzibbur. אמר לו רבי שמעון. Amar lo Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon answered back. והלא אלו פרים ואלו אילים ואלו כבשים, Vehalo
elu parim ve'elu eilim ve'elu kevasim,
that some of them are oxen and rams and some are sheep.
אלו בלילתן עבה, Elu belilatan avah, you know, those the the what
do you call it, the ox and the rams are a thicker
type of a of a mixture because it is one לוג log
for every, I gotta get this right again, two לוג log for
every עשרון isaron is the the ox. The ox is is 6
לוג log for 3 עשרון isaron. and the ram is 4 לוג
log for 2 עשרון. isaron. It's a two to
one. ואלו בלילתן רכה, Ve'elu belilatan rakah, and the sheep is three
to one. It's three לוג log for one עשרון. It's a so
it's more liquidy. אלו בלילתן שחרית ואלו בלילתן בין הערביים. Elu belilatan
shacharit ve'elu belilatan bein ha'arbayim. Some are in the morning like the
תמיד של שחר, tamid shel shachar, some are in the afternoon or
in the late afternoon, you know, מוסף, musaf, תמיד של בין הערביים.
tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. They're not all brought at the same time.
They're not allowed to be mixed and they're not all brought at
the time the same time. ואין נבללין זה עם זה, Ve'ein nivlalin
zeh im zeh, and they're not mixed together. So you can't use
that as a standard. The ציבור tzibbur never brings a unit of
61. So אמרו לו אמור אתה. Amru lo emor atah. So they
said to him, okay, so if you don't like our reason, you
give a reason. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them. הרי
הוא אומר וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן וחרבה, Harei hu omer vechol mincha
belulah vashemen vecharevah,
any מנחה mincha mixed with oil or dry. ואמרה תורה תהא מנחה
שיוכלו להיבלל. Ve'amrah Torah tehei mincha sheyuchlu lehibalel. A מנחה mincha has
to be able to be mixed with the oil. And more and
you know, more than 60 עשרונות isronot cannot mix well with oil.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him. בששים נבללין בששים
ואחד אין נבללין? Beshishim nivlalin beshishim ve'echad ein nivlalin? What, 60 is
fine, 61 is no good? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said back
to them. כל מדות חכמים כן הן. Kol middot chachamim ken hen.
Yeah, that's the way the sizes of the Sages are. The sizes
of the rabbis were. בארבעים סאה הוא טובל, Be-arbaim se'ah hu tovel,
you can go to a מקוה Mikveh 40 סאה. se'ah. בארבעים סאה
חסר קורטוב, Be-arbaim se'ah chaser kortuv, 40 סאה se'ah minus a thimble,
אינו יכול לטבול. Eino yachol litbol.
It doesn't work. So far pretty much like the משנה, Mishnah, except
a little more explicated about בלילה קטנה blilah katana and בלילה רבה.
blilah rabba. And here another example about a שיעור shiur of the
חכמים. chachamim. כביצה Ke-beitzah מטמא טומאת אוכלין metamei tumat ochlim if something
is the size of an egg, it can become טמא tamei as
food because it's able to be like eaten in one swallow, you
know. פחות מכביצה, Pachot mi-kebeitzah, כביצה חסר שומשום, ke-beitzah chaser shumshum,
the size of an egg minus the size of a sesame seed,
אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין. eino metamei tumat ochlim. It's not. What's the
big deal? It's just a sesame seed. שלשה על שלשה Sheloshah al
sheloshah מטמא מדרס, metamei midras,
three, you know, טפחים tfachim by three טפחים tfachim is an, it
creates טומאת מדרס, tumat midras, something that's like a something that if
you sit on it, it's like a seat, it's a piece of
cloth and it's worth sitting on for like, you know, for like
זב zav and זבה zavah and נדה, niddah, etc. שלשה על שלשה
חסר נימא אחת,
Sheloshah al sheloshah chaser
nima achat, but three טפחים tfachim by three טפחים tfachim minus one
little thread אחת, achat, אינו מטמא מדרס. eino metamei midras.
Okay? Yes. So that's the שיעור. shiur. Okay. Fine. That's a reasonable
answer. What? Then the גמרא Gemara asks this question. וכי אין נבללין
מה הוה? Veki ein nivlalin mah havah? Okay, but who cares if
you can't mix it together? והתנן Ve-hatnan didn't we teach אם לא
בלל כשר im lo balal kasher that even if you didn't mix
the oil with the flour, it's still כשר? kasher? So now we
have a famous statement of רבי זירא. Rebbe Zeira. אמר רבי זירא,
Amar Rebbe Zeira, said רבי זירא, Rebbe Zeira, כל הראוי לבילה אין
בילה מעכבת בו. Kol hara'ui le-blilah ein blilah me'akevet bo.
Anything that theoretically could be mixed together, the failure to mix it
does not prevent it from being valid. So if it's the proportions
that the mixture could work, it's still valid without mixing. וכל שאינו
ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו. Ve-chol she-eino ra'ui le-blilah blilah me'akevet bo.
But if it's not fit, it doesn't even have the ability to
be mixed together, then the fact that it's not mixed actually means
it's not valid because it isn't even the right, you know, quantities
that could be mixed. All right, now that on its own is
just a reasonable statement. You know, once you sell a חידוש chidush
that you don't actually have to mix it, you could understand that
if the תורה Torah says בלול בשמן, balul ba-shemen, mixed, and then
somehow we learn from somewhere that בדיעבד bedieved it's okay if it's
not mixed, you could understand, okay, but the demand of בלול balul
is still telling you that it has to be theoretically able to
be mixed. Makes total sense when you start with a demand and
then you learn from somewhere that that's not strictly required, you can
wind up in the middle ground. What is interesting is that sometimes
the גמרא Gemara uses, you know, רבי זירא's Rebbe Zeira statement כל
הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו kol hara'ui le-blilah ein blilah me'akevet
bo to just on its own say, okay, so you can't meet
this requirement. As long as it's theoretically possible, whatever the requirement is
under discussion, as long as it's theoretically possible, even if you didn't
practically meet it, as long as you could meet it, that's enough.
And of course that's not always true. Most of the time you
actually do have to really meet the requirement. So the question always
is when the גמרא Gemara uses this, how does the גמרא Gemara
know when a requirement is per se demanded and how does it
know when it's enough that it in theory could be satisfied? That's
not our topic, our topic is very concrete, our case, but it
is how the גמרא Gemara sometimes abstracts the principle of רבי זירא.
Rebbe Zeira. Okay, we will end here for now.